All right I think we'll go ahead and get started so my name is richard is
area high work in the dx organization
within microsoft with those not aren't familiar with that part of...microsoft its
developer experience so it's working with developers and really try and help developers
...their use of...developing tech...developer technologies
...might specialties really around obviously sixty-five although I do a lot of
things in the mobile space which is kind of what brought me to this session today
...excited to talk to you guys about this so, this topic is on
the building cross-platform mobile apps with our office three
sixty five api is
so I'll kind of set the ground a little bit in terms of this
...a introduction to cross-platform development although I'm going
to start pretty low and build-up I don't think I'll lose anyone
but I just want-to let-you know that there are more like introductory,
introductory sessions and I have some links to those later in
the de presentation today so I'm curious before I get started in and I
can't see that well out in the audience but I'll do my best to try to see who here
is came to this because they're interested in maybe cordova development?
Okay, how about zimmerman?
...so, a little half-and-half careers is we consider themselves someone that does
allotted or maybe a lot but has been development...sixty-five and
...api is interesting okay very cool I like I like that answer
one of the things that we talk about with
...sixty-five is the sheer magnitude of users that are using that
service in as a developer that's building applications you can really maximize on that
and get a big audience for the applications that you
right by targeting different services within office through sixty-five there's
not a great examples out there that you can go and, view that are in, you know,
all the different types of marketplaces to build do that.
Now out I have one other question I guess I'm who
...carries...as...they're kind of everyday phone is a windows phone.
Okay, about iphone an android.
All right so we're pretty decent
sport there so that's really what has driven us to do
a lot all-round cross-platform development talks you notice that ...doing more and more
...space investing more in tools to be able to deliver cross-platform
...you bring your own device movement
has really pushed organizations to be able to deliver applications on any
type of device it's very rare it's on occasion I'll talk to an organization where
they're like well we have a standardin maybe there's a standard your
orbit it's probably a menu of things like you can have maybe
an ios device or windows phone so that's what we commonly see and
that's really what is driving us doing a lot around this I have this kind
of token evaluation side the beginning and...of
you guys can win prizes it plus it's very important for us to get feedback on how we're doing in
the sessions so let's talk a little bit about kind of what we're going to do so the objectives of this
session our to explore the different options for building cross-platform mobile apps with the
office three sixty five api is we're going to try to discuss
how we integrate both office three sixty five and asher
because as your...as...directory is a dependency on working with
...sixty-five...going to talk about what are the unique constraints
of working with those with both cordova and zimmer
and projects we're also going to try to outline the different software
and service requirements so that you can build these types
of applications within visual studio of I know that you can build zebra and,
cordova apps in other id...this is really going to focus
...visual studio and that's obviously not the that's not the
...I guess the important part of this session the session is more about integrating with
...sixty-five so from a take away standpoint I hope you guys walk away knowing
that we have a comprehensive set of both...decays in api
...so that you can build cross-platform applications with
...sixty five of I mention that there are other id
easy can work with we do feel like visual studio will provide the
premier development experience for building especially with
office three sixty-five...I don't have to jump around to different places the register and app
and be able to get all the can sit permissions that I need and you'll see how
that works out and then finally there are pitfalls in building
...apps with cross-platform apps with the...sixty-five api...
all hurdles that we can get past...things that for some of the early people that
...built some cross-platform apps they dealt with those
in and that's good for you because there's a lot of lessons learned that hopefully
will reduce any sort of the challenges the...
run into just a level set I know that it was kind of split between cordova and
...and let me just a kind of give a little bit of realization this is how I'm going to
attack those objectivesso, we're going to talk about native applications with the
office three-six with obviously sixty-five...a little bit different from a traditional application that connects
office three sixty five...it's been seven point seven five minutes on that there's some
been pretty exact there but you'll see why we're going to spend thirty minutes on
cordova and twenty on the cameron so-if that upset
...I apologize the reason I'm doing it this way is that we actually have
an entire dedicated session on the...and front for office three sixty five
it's on friday ...from examine and checks from the one of
...sixty-five product groups is going to be leading that so we don't have a deeper
divx specific to cordova so I decided to give it a little bit more love in this session so just
to set the stage that's kind of what we're going to do for this and, then
...to...at the...for qa and that should leave
you with exactly fifteen seconds extra time in this box and,
you can, you know,
turn around and give good...based upon that...got fifteen seconds back your day I...
guys got a laugh lighten up a little bit with me I also have a laser here so I will use it?
From a developer vision hopefully you guys have seen this slider a
...deviation of it this is talking about kind of what our vision
is a of developing applications with office three sixty five we
...have two approaches one is being able to extend the
opposite experience and the other is taking office in bringing it into
my experience that's really what we're concentrating on here right is going to build my application
a standalone mobile application that might want to connect
...be able to take advantage ofnot only the great services that...sixty-five
offers but also being able to take advantage of that large audience that we
have of subscribers within...sixty-five so that's really kind
of the vision that we have around this encourage you guys
too if I know there was not many people that raise their hand on the
...sixty-five developer front we have some really
great sessions this week I encourage you to check them out we also some cool swagger have some awesome like
...if you go down to the to the booth all right.
So, let's talk a little bit...native office three sixty five apps in as
you're eighty so I want to start with a little level set around our office three
sixty five api eyes and I think that's especially fitting for those that might be new to this that
are that are in the room so first of all we have really standardized on trying to provide
a comprehensive set of api is that are going to follow technology
standards so we're going to deliver api is that are
delivered via restondata they're going to be secured using...from
...austin point what...leveraging is as...active directory so if
you didn't know every single user in office three sixty
five the identity provider for them
is asher active directory sometimes if you if your organization is in
...sixty-five that can sometimes be confusing because you get taken to your login
page that's just a federated login that takes you back and allows us to
...impersonating you with the user account that's
been synchronized into the cloud so that's really important is that not only is
asher id going to be the identity store for users its where we're going
to register applications and that's going to give us something that we call the as
you're eighty common consent framework and you may have not heard that term but the idea
behind this is of authenticate my user one-time and then once
I authenticate them I can reach into all the different services that leverage as
you're active directory so those that's all the services of office three
sixty-five like exchange online and sharepoint online one note but,
it also extends out to other things we'll talk about that briefly.
...a little bit we support in abstracted directory the
concept of a delegated permission and application
permission so the difference between those two are one is operating as the user
one is operating at a higher-level as like an application as like a service account
...has higher-level permissions so when I go and leverage
and application one of the benefits of using as you're active directory co-op
is as a mobile developer you don't have to deal with
login you don't have to store username in passwords you probably are going to
have to have some concept of the user perhaps but,
that user can simply mapped to something that you get back from
an identity...as...active directory so that's a pretty key
...in a value propped we sayabout
...is the identity provider for some of the apps that you...
We support...it all types of apps both native
at in web applications from
...protocol standpoint we do provide a lot of fine-grained permissions so you can
build applications that might just have read access to
contact or maybe it has for permission to sharepoint to do anything
any site collection so there's a lot of different granular permissions
that we can work with within this what you're seeing here is actually
and authorization dialogue because it's a lot if you've ever done anything with what you've
seen it probably...dialogue pop-up that says hey this app wants
to leverage some data that you have in office three sixty five and,
you see this all over the web if you ever been on facebook in clicked on app in
there you get that prop that says hey this company wants to be able to post on your behalf
and get every information that you've ever posted inside...that's the same
concept here so as we explore the authentication components of this and
api is that we have we have a pretty comprehensive list of api is that you
can be able to connect into so this first list these are the what we
call the launch services these are the services that we are originally made
available when we introduced the concept of the office three sixty five api
...is about a year-ago so we have things like my files which is one drive for business we can go to
sites calendar
contact we can work with mail we can work what users in groups that are an active
directory some of the new services and some of these are not even sure
of been completely announced they're going to be announced this week but there's a number of new services
I'm not even sure I have the full list here but one note with office three
sixty five is something that's lining up to where you can go and get one
note notebooks that might be secured behind corporate locations
user profiles manage metadata the new video services within
office three sixty-five modern groups the office grab you've heard a lot about the office
...and being able to get rich data out of there.
But, one of the things I want to point out is that idea
of common consent it goes beyond just the opposite three sixty
five things there's lots of other applications that connect with as
you're active directory and we can use those as well.
You can see over on the right-hand side there's
other services that I could connect into excusing high-power by I
connect into dynamic crm.
There's a number of third-party applications not applications that microsoft
built but other isv maybe even your own applications
so you might have multiple applications that you developing and produce for
either customers or within your organization those can show up here as well and
get granular permissions so that idea of comic consent is very powerful from that
standpoint so that's the kind of the groundwork around
...active directory and how it plays with...sixty-five?
One important thing to talk about here is what's unique about native apps
so when you go can create an app inside of asher active directory you have a choice you could
create what we call web app or native app and, there are some key differences in
a native app so if you've ever worked with these before there's a few things are going to
need it no one is a native app is inherently multi
...so when I go when I build a web app in as
you're active directory I have a little toggle switch that lets me say I want this to be single tenet for my
...or I wanted to be...to where anyone can use it mobile apps don't have that
concept they're allthey all use a what we call the
common in point which means they can they are inherently multi
tenet now you could hard code the authority that you use through
authentication will look at that a little bit but they are inherently multi tenet?
No, client app or there's no secret so if you worked with
...before a lot of times you have an app idea nap secret and you use that in
this little dance is...walk flow in order to get an access token
ob you don't have the concept of a secret and it's actually a good reason if you think about
apply built-in app that secret is like my password to the world and if I
...go in distribute that on every device out there there's going
to be someone that savvy enough to go and pull down maybe the app package
dissected and find that secret so we don't actually distribute a secret in
a native app.
They're going to use.
A web authentication broker...handle by
...which is the...are active directory authentication libraries...look at this but,
ultimately even though it's a native apps so if it's,
you know, ios you have a...that
your ui built-in if it's windows you have example file...android you might have
an xml file regardless of that when you go to authenticate we're going to launch up
basically a browser window of it's going to it's going to be the office three
sixty five login page or if you're the your customers...it would be their
login page that's an important thing is we don't we want the user to have confidence
that it is like a legitimate source that's collecting their information?
We provide a number of api is...we don't provide any sort of controls are
not yet at least there's talk about maybe building some things
that people pickers and things like that you can easily dropping your applications but for now it's really just going to
be in points that you connect...
...then finally for
a mobile app you cannot use what we mentioned earlier which
was app only permissions you could only operate as the user now there are
ways around this you could have a service that you host that does do app permissions
that you proxy through so if I wanted to let's say I needed to
create a new site collection sharepoint and that usually might take a
...permission why could submit to a service that's running
apple only and be able to do that so there are ways around that but natively on the device you're only going
to be able to operate as the user.
All right so let's jump into.
A patchy cordova and like I said we'll
spend a around thirty minutes on this depending on time all kind of monitor the time and then
we'll move on to the next component so if your brain you
...again this was an introductory session for cordova
...I'm also not going to try to debate
on which one should you use I don't even think it's not a apples to apples
comparison I think one is really geared towards a web developer and
...really geared towards a dot net developer I know that sometimes a
dot net developer can be a web developers that's where you're...have to make those types of decisions but
...cordova standpoint cordova is the same thing
is phone gap innocent so if you haven't heard of cordova you probably
maybe part of phone gap but the idea of this is you're going to build all of
your mobile app natively in html five javascript
in css...now you're going to be able to use all kinds of rich plugins to make
it feel native it doesn't have to feel like a web page you don't see
the and address bar or anything like that that's all hidden from the user and it can
it's actually deployed to the device it runs local you can be offline
and user cordova app in order to work with these with inside
...visual studio you need at least visual studio twenty thirteen with update
for and the visual studio tools for
cordova cp three-point-one you can look at it on the slide
...down if you want visual studio twenty fifteen it is part of the
...option when you go to the install wizard to be able...to pull this down I
warn you that to put the tooling inside of visual studio will put a lot of things on your computer so
...my primary development machine these days is a surface pro three that run it
...I five...it's not a super powerful machine and,
this is going to when you install these tools it's going to do things like activate hyper
...so that you can run
...different evaluators you can stop that so I tend to I stops the hyper
...service and I use devices mainly for a lot of my development there's also some other emulator
will look at that don't require you to have hyper v at all from
and, app registration this...gets a little bit interesting if I want to registered app with
...sixty-five or even have to go
...I can do it directly from within visual studio through what we call the
ad connected service wizard that's also how I could pull down the...the...actually
mentioned this before but for...three sixty five we of all of these rest
data in points but for a lot of the in points we've wrapped them
...sdk so you can work with strongly typed objects
and, it's really up to you which you feel more comfortable with from a dot net standpoint I
certainly like using the sdk in javascript it's not near is
...important because it's pretty easy to work with geis on in javascript
anyway but know that there is st case for both...and
...and I can pull those in through the ad connected service wizard or I can use new get to pull
those in when I when I build a cordova project in do the
add connected service wizard I'm going to get a bunch of assets that are added to my
project under the services slash office three sixty five folder so it's going to add
...a number of different script files I don't remember the exact number I think it's like ten
script files now the interesting thing is I don't have to go ad reference to all of those I just need to
add reference to one so there's athree sixty five loader dot js and it's going to
dynamically load all the scripts that you need into your cordova project a
few and additional tips and gotcha is so first of all in
cordova at the web authentication broker can be a little
bit tricky so the it'll automatically launch of window for you...
and provide a login experience but I've found that what I typically do as soon as I create
a new project is I go in and I add the browser plug-in again and that
...to resolve a lot of issues with that I think that the
original tooling it might be fixed in three-point-one but original tooling
was a little bit at least on ios it was a little bit flaky in terms of how it
...that whole login process another tip is the office three
sixty five loader
...go lower all these...but it doesn't tell you when that's done so if you are building
a mobile app that as soon as the mobile app was launch you wanted it to go through
and logged user in that's a little bit tricky to do
...certainly achievable I've done a few ways one is I've done like a set
time-out I've done things where I've change that office three sixty five...so
...use like a aj query get script so that
...actually get a call back when it's done loading all of those scripps because if
we go and try to go and do that whole authentication...
Before it's actually loaded it will
calls issues and finally in this is going to be pretty consistent between both cordoba
...you cannot build
...a and ios build
...the and debugged today on windows another some things in
the keynote this morning about being able to take objective see and being able to compile it but,
there's no way today on visual studio to actually go and
debug that on ios device so if you're going to do anything with ios
where that's iphone you really need a mac near you and that's why I have
...onstage years that I'm going to remote we connect to this it's going to be basically a
build box for me and, I can also use the emulator is on it or I can use a physical device but it's going
to ultimately be my...for that.
All right so let's do a demo
...try to make this pretty light on slides are going to spend more time actually building some
app so let me switch over and I know the first thing in a
says wow that's tiny...use zoom it I'll do a good job of using zoom
it so don't worry and I'll also zoom in on my code when we get things created so
...for now I'll create a new project and the
app the cordova project templates are actually going to be under javascript because remember
cordova is actually building a web page basically that's what it is so,
what I'm going to do is I'm going to create this apache cordoba app as a blank app and we'll
just call this and I'm going to organize a little bit better?
We'll call this the.
Look, up map.
Algal n create and this going to go off
...provision this template what you'll notice right off the bat is that it looks like web project
...because innocents is a web project so I have an
index dot html file I have a css folder ivan images folder
...a web project...differences it's going to be installed natively on a
device and run natively so let's do a few things you really quickly first is
since this is a native app that's going to run and use a html technologies
what's going out a few new get packages...add a few popular ones if you're in the web world let's
aj query is kind of hard to do much at all client-side these days without
j query that's the other thing if you're new to
cordoba is it's going to be a hundred-percent client-side there's no server-side component of this there
actually is in kind of a abstract...we'll talk about here just a moment let's.
Is finding?
...results for j query.
I'm on install your right thank you so much.
So, we'll just...query maybe bootstrap as well not just,
you know, the couple popular ones so go ahead jay query here.
And, now that I have these in here we can simply start putting
our page together and I'm going to do this really simple at first so
...index page...all kind of zoom in on is let's go and add references to those script file
so let's just add are.
Rj query come on.
What are reference...query?
What are reference to bootstrap?
...add are cs bootstrap css.
All right the other thing that this gave us automatically is
an index of page and, actually I probably should but these are the bottom line page you see here a
...created this index dot js file by look at the
index dot js file it basically has some device ready events
or some device based events so it's telling me when all of the things of loaded
...ready to actually start running my code on this device so you can see that here on this
document ready there's also...on pause and on resume if I wanted to
your built a mobile app you need to deal with the sometimes we call it...stoning where you
save the state maybe refresh that so if someone comes back to the...can keep on
moving forward so what I'm going to do is before I do anything else I'm going to make this
...office three sixty five at summer come out your ominously ad connected service and
...zoom in on this you can see this result easy we make it so just go
ad connected service and this is going to launch a wizard to pull in and
register, register app...all of the resources that you need
...that wizard you can see that I can quick register my app this can actually
...and sermon a log in with one of my.
Tenet user accounts.
And, now it's going to show me all the different services that
are available to me and actually this is a little bit outdated we haven't updated the to-ing completely there's a
lot more services that are available I mention some of those like one note user profiles all
these different things but for now let's just add a few things let's maybe add
...permission to do single sign on or enable sign on to use to read the
user's profile but maybe go over to sites and do what's read ride
...all site collections you can see there's a service and
...their scopes for the service so if I wanted to maybe read
contacts I can just do read contact on here all right the next thing that
we'll do here is you'll see that it adding all of these scripts for me so
it's going loading all of these into my project and...it's going to give me a little bit of
...a starter page some like a read me
to show me how to get working with this so what I'll do is I
...to go and add reference to that office three
sixty five loader so if we look over in my solution explore under office
three sixty five you can see there's a bunch of scripted added so there's a number of different
scripts that help me deal with different things so there's one for exchange type of things there's
one for sharepoint because I added services to permissions to both but there's also this
one but it's called the office three sixty five loader if we look at this
is where it's basically just something that loops through all the other script files and
adds those for us so there are to go and at each one individually
to my index page the other interesting thing that a
added here is there is actually a settings page or setting script
file that has things like my app id and how I'm going to go and
redirect to get an access token so this right
here if you've worked with adjective director the fact that it says common?
That's actually indication that this is a multi tenet app so if it wasn't multi tenet
...you typically specify the tenet here so,
like microsoft-dot-com or whatever your company is dot com
so this is multi tenant we have our redirect...going to handle all of that for us we can
simply startwriting some code so what I'll do is let me just I'm...to just for fun
...put an ordered list on my page and a button and we'll give them
...name...give us an idea of.
The list...put a button here.
And, we'll give this make a little bit prettier we'll give it a button, button primary.
And, button block these are just some
bootstrap values and let's go and just call this get contacts.
All right so I'll go ahead and say this...really quickly and what we
...now do is kind of wire that up inside of our index page you can see right here it says
...as been loaded perform any additional in initialization
that you need so what I'm going to do is ...just do a quick document ready?
And, inside of
...up a quick...so we're going to do are button click which was the button.
We're do a quick on that.
All right so now we need to actually connect...and get the users contacts
so the way we're going to do that is using some of those javascript files that added
for sets the sdk now I could certainly try to do everything manually but they've
done a lot of work for you automatically so things like I don't want to get
too deep on like how often works withyou know, off but one of the things I'm going to get back is something called
a refresh token refresh token applied if I
...that on the phone the user will never have to login every time they use the
...automatically keep them sign in if you choose to implement a pattern like that which I
think's a good experience you want to user app to type in I hate...on these little keyboards so it's
...all that for me so let's take a look at out easy it is for us to do that's what I'm going to
do is first define and...with the cool thing is when we go to
zimmer and it's going to be almost identical instead of being...javascript I'm
...be in csharp but you'll see that it's almost identical in how I do this so let's do a
var and we'll call this off context we're going to make
the sequel to a new three sixty five...dot context.
And, from here what I'm going to do
is initialize this to go and get the first of
to tokens so if you again if there's something if you're we've worked with a lot
before usually I get a context token first and it returns for me
a code and then I go get an access token that I can use to actually perform
operations so that's what I do year we'll go ahead and get our access token so
...context token...say.
Let's see all context ...
Token.
...pass this in a service in this case we're going
to connect to outlook so we're going to say outlook dot office
...sixty five.
After that this will return us.
...token.
We'll call this the see token this is the context token
...another token...a moment but...going to be the first one that we work with the second token
...is the actual access token is...to be them important one that's going to do all
the work for us that's going to allow us to actually get access to things so we'll call this and,
this is going to use a special function for this...going to call this are eighty function
...just our access token function it's going to be the see token.
Dot get.
Access token function.
In the summer do the same...basically
the same this is what we call resource so everything that I connect to an office three sixty
five has a resource id they can be different things for one node it's www one
...dot com for
...sharepoint it's actually the sharepoint sites it's
base url is basically saying this is the resource I want to get access to
so I'm specifying that resource that I want to get access to and then I can actually
go and us get a client start working with the api so what I'm going to
say is new microsoft.
And, for some reason intelligence is ag intelligence usually works with these not sure outlook.
Services dot client I believe is what I need...in this I need a
...the in point that I'm going to call into so,
this is actually going to be I can...data in point so where I'd actually go and make a rest
call and for this is going to...ws.
Slashdata so it's basically
...data in point of exchange web services and then I also need to pass this
my access token function so I'm going to put in my
at function so it's basically words and it's initialize
...this client which is again going to be strongly typed where I can go and work with it but,
it's going to take that access token function so that it can do it
needs to now I can simply start working with this so I can say client dot me.
Dot contracts.
Dot get contacts.
And, that will return me call back with my contacts.
And, for now let's just...break pointing here.
And, see if we were successful up until this point so there's a few different options I have for debugging
these one is the visual studio tools for apache code over going to give me something called ripple,
ripple is an in chrome browser emulator for enjoyed
it it's not going to help me with ios but
...helps me with things like android so I'll go ahead and use ripple
once I find ripples really useful as I'm making quick changes like case
this didn't quite work I'll try something else because what happens in ripple is as soon as I make a change and I
...visual studio it automatically
read innocence refresh is the app so I get a really
fast way to do development now at some point I probably want to test on real
device...the second time around when we do this will actually
use a real device I will tell you that ripple I have
mixed experience with sometimes it loads immediately like the second I press
...five sometimes which it looks like we're getting right now because
obviously demo god's going to be happy with us it's going to wait for a little bit in fact it
may we might even get a little dialogue that says it's not responding just like that and,
actually we just say wait the patient it will load
...is all the additional changes you make
they update immediately so you might just have to wait the first-time you launch these
so we'll give this a just another quick second.
I will say well this is loading because this is html five and javascript you can really use
any really any type of script you might want to reference so I'm a big fan of angular so I
build almost all of microbe apps with angular pretty much all those in fact there's a really cool
framework called iconic that I've gotten really popular but using in these...apps
...combines some really great mobile ui because that's one thing you'll notice here is
your kind of in charge of building the...your own user interface
you get native controls zimmer is going to give me native controls on the device...button is going to
look like a ios button or an android button whereas here it's going to look
...bootstrap button because that's the styling that I used...
going quick get contact this is going to launch into.
A new window or it should launch...new window...my.
Id wrong there's a pretty cool thing too is I get a live dom explore in
...if I wanted coming here and actually change the text to say hello world.
Immediately changes it so it's pretty,
pretty cool from that standpoint but for some reason is did not hit
...its try hitting our...point here?
What's that you're right thank you gosh you guys are
...me today forgot a pounded...of my from a selector
j query so all I did was refresh and it's already refresh the app for me so now if I say
get contacts.
There we are break point and now it should...me through
an overall process now and ripple the way that's going to work is it's going
to launch into a new window and I think I may have already mystic matured again.
Three sixty five or.
I did not load my hello dot js so let's do that here really quickly thank you.
So, our loader is under a services.
Slash.
Office three sixty five.
And, moi under scripts.
And, we're duo three sixty five.
All right last try and then I'm going to pull the completed one out of an so we'll go and
refresher...refreshed...could ended...probably still not referencing it right
me jump over to one...that's done just to kinda give you the experience of this one also and,
the cool thing is this one that I'm going to go jump over to there's
not this is all of the code for the entire project so I know that small don't worry about it but the
point is this does a lot with very little code this is actually using
...you can see I have a function that gets
an access token I'm using a cool cordova plug-in for barcode
scanning so actually what I did is this is like a
physical records management scenario where I have a warehouse of physical records and I want
to store reference to them and sharepoint so I have a bunch of barcode...that I
print-out that reference actual list items inside of a sharepoint library so,
you can see here I'm just doing a simple get in this case so I can use the rest api
I don't have to use the sdk...then when that basically comes back I'm going to update my
...model that I'm using here inside of angular
...go and run this one and see if this will be...to happy with this?
I will apologized that mile android display app here is refresh is really slowly
so...this might be a little bit slow to refresh.
Forcing so it's in the background deploying here if you look at the top here I selected device
instead of instead of using one of the insulators is actually going to go on to a
...I can also debug to the
...unfunny to do that I run a special app over on the
...that allows me to basically do appearing so that I can do remote debugging
on that so looks like it is just about deployed year
...installing app on the device in the app is now launching on the device you can see it's a little
bit slower refreshing on-screen somebody coming here I get this empty user interface is
all built using ironic so it helps me do some kind of nice-looking ui but
...I want to do is let's say I'm out in the warehouse and I need to scan some
of the different physical records we have so I'm...go and quick scan remember this
is an html app but it's going to be able to do locally on the device
...pretty high and stuff so this is a little barcode
scanner plug-in homage coming here and let's skin this first guy.
Goes it captured it so it found the url now it's calling out to sharepoint and
now I can see it pulled all the data so I can see the title of this
...the category the business unit the building and the location in the building
I could go scan another one here and.
Pick it up it's going to go do the search in sharepoint and there goes it
does my update so open you can see I mean this is I mean that does that's pretty cool I mean that's
an actual real functioning apps something that could be valuable for an organization as data
...point and there is not much code this app
at all that hundred-percent of the code right here
...hails all the authentication for me university never prompted me to log in this time
because it stored that now I could clear the cash for that app and it would probably
...login but pretty powerful stuff what I can do with cordova.
All right so if you're more if you're interested in...there are some additional sessions you-can
go-to there's one on general ios android development they're going to
spend a little bit of time on cordoba...mainly going to be on some of our we have
...three sixty-five...that are native for things like x code
...android studio so you could go see those the other one here is
if you want just a general getting started with cross-platform mobile development with the
patch cordova there's another session on that has nothing to do top esri sixty-five
it just kind of the getting started for that high encourage it I've become a huge fan of what you
can do quickly in cordova all right let's turn our
attention to examine so if I want to develop a zimmerman again,
I can either developing visual studio twenty fifteen or twenty thirteen I
list visual studio twenty thirteen on your just because that is what we have
...in production today so
obviously...could go get visual studio twenty fifteen that's in a beta
...and you can work...as well for me to work with
...and I'm going to need to install zimmer in-studio
capital asterisks there because you should know apache cordova
it's free it is an open-source technology ...and there are
licensing cost associated with that that's just something to be aware of so zimmer studio if
you're msdn subscriber I believe that...depending on your...zimmer in
allows you to have a developer license to where you can you can develop and test apps and if
you wanted in producing app actually publish it out that's when you want to move up to like
an enterprise license of a
...you're going to have the same eds of working with our
api is inside of...projects you're going to be able to do the app registration through ad connected
service and, you're going to have the same way of pulling the st...down is to
add connected service you can also use new get for these obama actually show you
were going to look at some more...some alpha type things that I can do on released
things that make it a really good experience examine that use pure new get
versus using that ad connected service but I just know that it is
it can be that easy is just saying ad connected service from a solution structure if you are
...zimmer gives you a couple options you can build
a platform specific right so let's say your entire organization uses iphones
or your entire organization use is android devices however
...dot net shop that's a great scenario for
examining right you can have your developers that developing dot net
...platforms and you can build a platform specific app in zimmer
...visual studio so I can pick this is
only for ios however there's also what we call a shared project
...project looks a lot like the first version of
all windows universal...if you've ever done a windows
universal lap before you add a windows project
windows phone project...have a shared projects
the shared project is retry put all your code because it can be shared across all of those and this
is exactly what it looks like when you're in a shared project
...I can have platforms specific code it's going to
have basically...app forwindows phone app for ios
and app for android I can put app specific code in
...but I also can?
Re-use a lot of code in
a shared project and that's really the goal that I would I would challenge you on
is try to have the same code as much as possible when you're building these types
...projects and if you go to the session on friday that
james in...are doing they built a really cool application that almost a
hundred-percent of it is done in the shared project...do a few
ui specific things they want to take advantage of some of the app specific things and,
they can do that with semen a few gotcha is to know about so,
one of those actually one other thing I should note is the another option
...can use what they call zimmer informs which is their own kind of form
framework that then gets kind of it gets translated to a device
specific control so if I put there...zimmer informed button on
a page...innocence render and iowa's button or an android button so
...like they're a native control but you also have the ability of leveraging
native layout so in the new versions of...I can actually work with
...storyboards and I can work with the actual xml layouts for
...android app...you got
...but again if you're going to do anything on...you have to have a
...to be able to...and debug against you musc.
Create what we call a binding project if you want
to use the as our active directory authentication libraries so, that's a
value hear me say a lot basically what the adjective directory libraries
are it's basically it makes.
Authentication against asher disney simple like really,
really simple where, you know, after bright lines and lines and lines of code you can
write like three lines of code authenticated handles all of that including the caching of tokens
now what we've done is we've created native versions of eight-hour on all the major
mobile platform so we have one for windows we have one for ios we have one for
androidand, instead of building like
...special version just for examine what we've done is you can go and
...in a binding version of those
secret binding project of those eight...simply is
...or those eight-hour libraries and bring those into your
...project so, this is a little bit of a pain I put it in kind of a
gotcha because it's a little bit of a pain to do now that being said what I'm
going to demonstrate today is what we call eight-hour version three it's
and alpha preview so if you go on...victoria's blog he
has a lot of information on this but this unify...the experience I'm
going to be able to have a common way that I authenticate and I don't have to build those binding
...so it is an...so it is subject
to change but I want to show you how easy it is to use that approach is
...in project I think maybe james and...are going
to cover maybe a little bit of both but I'm going to I'm going to cover it that way I put in
the slides here I'm going to ask for a very specific version of this
...so the three dot one-dot to in all bunch of other numbers that I'm not going to try to recite
that one provides the most consistency that I've found across
bothios and android.
And, windows types of projects so let us
jump into a demo.
I'm going to.
...new project year in visual studio.
...a new project and what you'll see if I
apply explored csharp here...things you see that
...ios projects if you look in...I can go and create I need
of ios project these are...templates that allow me to do that I can also target just
android river so those are those platform specific types of projects that I might
want to build a here and there's a number of different you know,
interesting apps that I can do including...have apple watched inputs that I can go...and build
things and it's amazing now what I'm going to do is actually go to mobile
apps and this is where I can start creating a shared project
where I can innocence try to shares much codes I can across all of the different
...a project for every platform I could remove one if I wanted to out
...to keep all three but is going to give me windows ios
...now...you see there's kind of two flavors of each of these there is the
zoom informs version and then there's the native version so the difference between
these two is if I want to leverage the native layout so
fide like working with, you know, iowa storyboards I can use that
year I can actually mix them if I wanted to but what I'll do is I'll go ahead and do this
native one and we'll call this my...sample?
...is going to crank away and what you're going to find is it's going to create a number of
different projects within my solution we're...for we're going-to have to?
...where'd fthree.
Real projects that actually compiled
...have a shared project the share project you should know doesn't have
any references of its own it's going to use the references or whatever project your building
so it's really just class files...you put out here ...did you.
All right so let's just explore this...quickly what this looks like
you can see I have a basically a shared project which is just if
you're looking here notice there's not a references folder I can't do any references year I
have a android project of an ios project...a windows phone project ...
I could do now is I could simply go and add a connected service to these projects
I could go through that whole ad connected services wizard this would pool in all of the different
...case that I might want to now what I'm going to do for the sake
of this demo is I'm not going to take that approach the main reason for that is I want
to I want to use some of those that new eight-hour version three so I'm actually going to
use new get for that and I copy this in my one note here to make sure I grab the right
...going grab.
This m just going to use my package manager consul.
To go in pool in the specific version
that I want some of first do that.
For my ios project if you look here.
You select the project if you haven't work with new get in a multi project app you basically sucked the
project you...so it's added to ios now...exact same thing the android here.
So, now it's going to its added those and I can start taking
advantage of all the greatness that this new library affords me
so the first thing I might want to do is let's start putting some common code that
I'm going to share across all of my projects so the first thing I'm going to do is
...I didn't do ad connected services wizard one thing that I did do ahead of time
its at created justice settings helper this is basically where I've
just put in things like my client id which is a guid that adjective
directory knows about this has things like some of the resources that I might call it's really just a
constance file in fact I'll pasting here and I'll just proved that?
I'm going to change the name space that puts...you can see it's just it's
constance that's all it is and, this will just make it easy for me to get
going quicker so, what I'm going to do is just change my namespaces that we can quickly use that
...the next thing I want to do is I'm going to create and off helper and this is
really the crux of this demonstration is I'm going to show you how easy it is for us to
do authentication in-house how similar it's going to be to what we did in
the cordova project...class here and we'll just call...author helper?
...the great things that examine does is
they work really closely with microsoft to do so that when I write
something and maybe a modern type of syntax inside of dot net is trained
slates of to when it gets it goes through mono to be deployed to
...device or to android so,
I'm going to be able to do all the advance things that they are might want to do...I can do like
...type of functions so let's do just really quickly the key to getting any data out of
office three sixty five is working with access token so
...create a quick in point what do a public a
...static.
And, return string which is basically our access token
...call this get.
Access.
Token for resource.
When I mention common...only I have to authenticate once but I am going to have to go
and get it's an access token to any resource that I go and talk to now you're never going to get
...happens all behind-the-scenes but I'm going to go ahead and just put the resource here we're going to
...for resource if you remember what we did in our first project
our record look up we got...off context and then from there I started working
with tokens and that's exactly what I'm going to do here so let's do a...all
We're going to equal a new authentication
context.
And, let's see this resolves and it does
so we go and actually it looks like I need to in this pass my
...why create that settings helper so I can coming here and say
settings helper dot ad authority this is basically if it again
...authority is important component of this offload
...basically says where does the user login at so if I were to go into
this settings helper you'll see that the authority is just...
this one hard coded I'll change it to common but it can just be
window or login out windows dot net such common so I can I can simply specify that
here from here I can start
requesting access tokens it's really that simple I can say all context dot.
Acquire access token.
Silence so there's two different ways
...and I know that's really hard to see but there is a silent and then there is a
non silent what this is I should try to get silently first what this will do is
it'll say hey have you already cash to refresh token to where I don't have to prompt the user
login and then if that fails as a
...what I would do is go and get it in the more invasive way where I
actually prompt the user with a login screen so ultimately to
go and authenticate and get an access token...go start calling raster go use
Are just a couple of lines of code...do have a completed
one here that I just called the sharepoint searcher if we look in my...
helper that I was starting to build this is exactly what I'm doing is I'm just doing I'm getting that
of authentication context I'm trying to
acquire token silently if that fails?
I just skip and go down to get the access token
in the loud way if you will what...do for fun here is let's actually
...to deploys or debug this on and iphone so,
what I'm going to do...switch over to my other screen here?
And, in the background you'll notice that I have another
...tool that allows me to...my pc with my
mac and its pared here to where when I quick debug.
It's going to go
establish a connection we can actually see what's happening behind-the-scene so you can actually this is the
...the my terminal that shows me what's going on behind the scenes between
...handshake so it's in the
process of deploying this out to the device and it's looks like it's just about done.
And, here...second we should see our app pop-up so it's
there's the install there's our app popping up and,
now when this initially loads.
...a second.
Actually we'll show you here is even though this is running on my...come back over here I'm
hitting break points on my pc so we can still have a really good experience of debugging
these but let me I'll go ahead and let these play through what you'll see here is it's going to
...me with that office three sixty five sign
in screen so I could go ahead and provide my credentials and then it would be able to give
me access to the resources that I wanted so I am out of time
...want to cover a couple things there are some great sessions if you want the
indep view of examine with office three sixty five is set-top one right here that
...and checks are going to be doing on friday highly recommended I've seen what they've built for
...are they got a great solution on get...be able to pull down and see out was built on there's
also getting started with zimmerman visual studio...on day three
as well so check those out here's a few helpful links that you can go grab we have
...ultimate guide to the eight-hour bindings where you can get that one
you get that specific new get version so download...if you want these.
We quickly.
I will hangout for questions but I did want to jump to just make sure you guys.
You guys do your valuations this really important for this conference to keep the quality up
of a presentations we need your feedback on things so make sure you go in and fill
out your eval's appreciate everyone staying I failed in terms of my time on
two minutes over I really appreciate you guys coming I'm happy to hang out here at the front
...answer the question you guys have about this thanks so much.